<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Letter from the Dutch. of Portsmaouth to Madam Gwyn, on her landing in France</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48086</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15666640</idno>
  <idno type="VID">104313</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240941895</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1518</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36340</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">15666640</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48086)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104313)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1152:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Letter from the Dutch. of Portsmaouth to Madam Gwyn, on her landing in France</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet (2 p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J.S.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Kéroualle, Louise-Renée de, --  Duchess of Portsmouth and Aubigny, 1649-1734 --  Humor.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Gwyn, Nell, 1650-1687 --  Humor.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Pas </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:104313:1"/>
            <head>A LETTER From the Dutch. of Portsmouth TO Madam GWYN, On HER Landing in <hi>FRANCE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TO tell you I arriv'd safe at <hi>Callis</hi> wou'd be too much trouble to you, that I had an ill Passage, or was Shipwrack'd by the way, wou'd give you occasion of too much Joy. That you may not miscarry between these two Extreams, nor break your, heart with Excess of either, I am willing to give you the most moderate Account of my Voyage, that the shortness of time, and tediousness of the Journey can afford: The Wands fair, the Sea smooth, and the Ship sound, (not every Plank three Inches assunder, as you wish'd at parting) I skip'd away as smoothly as you cou'd expect, in a Golden Chariot, that hopt into it out of a Wheel-barrow. All the Marriners were my Votaries, they look'd upon me as the Star by which they guided, and the Sea-Nymphs paid me Venerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for <hi>Neptune,</hi> whom they most obey, is but <hi>Charle's</hi> Vice-Admiral, and you may imagine what Influence I had upon him; he proffer'd me vast Treasure of <hi>Indian</hi> Gems, Gold and Pearl, if I wou'd interceed to make him Admiral; I took his Jewels, but for the rest (<hi>Pardonne Moy Madam</hi>) I have a Prince of my own, and for all <hi>Grafton</hi> is the Elder Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollin, I hope to see young <hi>Richmond</hi> Master of the Sea-Horse, as well as I and; he offer'd me many Civilities, and wou'd have come in for a snack with his Brother-Monarch, alleadging, I was <hi>Venus</hi> the Goddess, that sprung from the Sea, and for the better Peopleing of his Dominions, wou'd have got upon me a Generation of <hi>Maremaids;</hi> I told him, I was no <hi>Sea-Rat, Otter</hi> or <hi>Eele,</hi> though I wriggled through the Mud to the Throne, as well as your Self. Nor was I like a <hi>Frog</hi> or <hi>Vermine,</hi> Born in a Ditch, and Destin'd to Die there, as your Noble Predecessor: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I did you the Justice, to recommend him to your Lady ship, to whom, for your Extraction, he might have a juster Title; so that in a short time, you may expect a Visit from his Excellency, as well as from the <hi>Morocco,</hi> or (in case he do not think it worth his time) a Deputation of a <hi>Dutch Cargo,</hi> with a Ship's Crew of <hi>Hemmings,</hi> who love to lie sleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Brandy and Sippets, a Constitution able to allay the fury of such
<pb facs="tcp:104313:2"/>gross Stomachs. There are several Ladies at Court of the same Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency, to whom I cou'd recommend a Sea-Horse, Whale or Porpoise, or the Pump, Bolsprit, or Main-mast of our Ship, to serve instead of the Standard, or a Regiment of <hi>Swits</hi> from the King of <hi>France</hi> his Guards? But as the Ladies of <hi>England</hi> have the Honour to sit at the Head of the Board, I know they have Wit enough to Carve for themselves. They sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom set a good Bit pass their own Chaps, and let Twenty Dishes be presented at a Course, I know their Appetites will serve them to taste of all, and after all that, in the Evening will take a Collation with the Cook, or Butler, or a Snack with the Coachman at Night, rather than go Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periess to Bed. Yet these lie under no Circumstance of Lust or Intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, because their Husbands keep a frugal Table, though the Sawcy Page, or Liquorish Lacky, has often a finger in the Dish, before his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship hath wiped his Whiskers. But these are safe under the Cloak of a Husband, whilst you and I lie under the Censure of every Cobler and Tinker, that will take upon him to Order and Regulate affairs of State, even to the Bed-Chamber. Well! of all sorts of Whores, the Miss is the most Deplorable, Naked and Expos'd to the Lash of every Parish-Beadle, whilst Matrimonial Concupiscence passes invisible under that Vizard. The fawning Cuckold will vindicate his Wives Honour, to save his own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and is always a pushing in his own Defence, and well he may, for his Horns are generally the largest of all the Beasts in the Forrest. In truth, take my Advice, Marry and take up in time, before you be cast off, for you will find at my return, the Ebb will be so low, that the next Retrenchment must be upon the Whores. What though it be some honest Tapster, or strong-water-man, 'twill serve to keep up your Spirits with the Dregs of Pots and Quarterns, when Age draws upon you; or strike up with some lusty Jocky at <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wmarket.</hi> You are of so true a Breed, while he has you by the Bit, he cannot want a Runner; besides, you may make a hand of it, and bring in Ten to One of the Lay, by going Booty, while you are in Riding-Case, no matter who Mounts the Saddle. The best Gennet, when she is past Service, is thrown to the Dogs. It may be your Fate, since Wrinckles, Age and Ugliness, the Tyrants of Loves Empire, have already Usurpt the Throne of Beauty, and have a care you fall not a Fee to the Grooms of the Stable, when you are no longer fit for the Royal Game. This (<hi>Madam</hi>) if you mind in time, is the last and best Advice can be given from</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Frined <hi>PORTSMOUTH.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. S.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>